<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A vindication of the principles of the author of the answer to the compiler of the nubes testium from the charge of popery in answer to a late pretended letter from a dissenter to the divines of the Church of England : as deceivers, and yet true, 2 Cor. 6. 8.</title>
            <author>Gee, Edward, 1657-1730.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1688</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 79 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42580</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G464</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3563</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11790673</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11790673</idno>
            <idno type="VID">49186</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42580)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 49186)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 531:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A vindication of the principles of the author of the answer to the compiler of the nubes testium from the charge of popery in answer to a late pretended letter from a dissenter to the divines of the Church of England : as deceivers, and yet true, 2 Cor. 6. 8.</title>
                  <author>Gee, Edward, 1657-1730.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Henry Mortlock ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Edward Gee. Cf. DNB.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gother, John, d. 1704. --  Letter form a dissenter to the divines of the Church of England.</term>
               <term>Gee, Edward, 1657-1730. --  Answer to the compiler of the Nubes testium.</term>
               <term>Church of England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:49186:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur,</p>
            <p>Hic Liber cui Titulus (<hi>A Vindication of the Principles of the Author,</hi> &amp;c.)</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Dec.</hi> 14. 1687.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Jo. Battely.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:49186:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A VINDICATION OF THE PRINCIPLES OF THE AUTHOR of the <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the <hi>Compiler</hi> of the Nubes Teſtium From the Charge of POPERY.</p>
            <p>In Anſwer to a late Pretended <hi>Letter from a Diſſenter to the Divines of the Church of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>As Deceivers, and yet True, <bibl>2 Cor. 6.8.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Henry Mortlock</hi> at the <hi>Phoenix</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-yard. 1688.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:49186:1"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:49186:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="vindication">
            <pb facs="tcp:49186:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:49186:3"/>
            <head>A VINDICATION OF THE PRINCIPLES OF THE AUTHOR of the <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the <hi>Compiler</hi> of the <hi>Nubes Teſtium,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>HAD I not already promiſed the world in Print a ſpeedy <hi>Vindication</hi> of my ſelf, the natural care and tenderneſs that every man hath for his own Reputation are a ſufficient engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to ſet about the clearing of my ſelf from being <hi>that Counterfeit,</hi> or teaching <hi>that Popery</hi> I am accuſed of in a Pretended <hi>Letter from a Diſſenter to the Divines of the Church of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have already hinted to the world in the <hi>Advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:49186:4"/>at the end of my <hi>Second Letter</hi> to <hi>Sabran</hi> the <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> that I am very well ſatisfied not onely that this <hi>pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Letter</hi> came out of <hi>Henry Hill's Preſs,</hi> but that <hi>it</hi> was the <hi>Iſſue</hi> of the <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s (or <hi>Compiler</hi>'s, call him whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you will) malicious Pen.</p>
            <p>This, every one that I converſe with, as well as my ſelf, quickly ſaw, and every man elſe cannot but ſee, that either knows the <hi>Print</hi> of <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> or the <hi>Stile</hi> of the <hi>Repreſenter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having made this diſcovery of their unhanſom un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derhand-dealings herein, I was once thinking to have ſhewn how very conformable this management was to the <hi>Secret Practices</hi> of <hi>ſome</hi> of the <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> in former times againſt the Eſtabliſhed <hi>Church of England;</hi> but when I found <hi>Materials</hi> increaſe too much upon my hands, which would have made an <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction</hi> too large for ſuch a <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> as I intend <hi>this</hi> to be, I have upon <hi>that,</hi> and a <hi>better reaſon</hi> laid that deſign aſide.</p>
            <p>I cannot however but tell the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> here, that I have read and conſidered his <hi>Third Chapter</hi> in his <hi>Third Part of Popery Miſrepreſented and Repreſented</hi> about <hi>the Jeſuits in Proteſtant Pulpits:</hi> And that I found neither <hi>Truth</hi> nor <hi>Reaſon</hi> there, as I think I could make appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent unto the world, were not <hi>this</hi> a <hi>Subject</hi> too nice for the <hi>preſent Age.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will tell him alſo, that it would have been as pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in him not to have touched upon this ſtring, ſince this is a <hi>Subject,</hi> in the treating of which he doth inevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tably run himſelf upon hurting either <hi>his Cauſe</hi> or <hi>his Conſcience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Among the <hi>Methods</hi> made uſe of againſt the <hi>Church of England,</hi> there is none more likely to have ruined the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:49186:4"/>
               <hi>Church,</hi> than <hi>that</hi> which was ſo much in vogue in the late <hi>King's Reign.</hi> I mean the beginning and keeping up of <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies</hi> againſt the <hi>Church,</hi> as if <hi>her Greateſt</hi> as well as moſt <hi>Learned Members</hi> had been at beſt <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhly affected,</hi> and waited onely for a good opportunity either of ſtepping over unto the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> or at leaſt of <hi>accommodating Matters</hi> with <hi>Her,</hi> and meeting her <hi>half way.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How ſucceſsful this falſe and moſt unreaſonable <hi>Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> of the <hi>Church of England</hi> was, no <hi>perſon</hi> can be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that remembers <hi>even</hi> the <hi>laſt part</hi> of the late <hi>King's Reign.</hi> What ſhare <hi>ſome</hi> of our <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s <hi>Friends</hi> had in the raiſing or fomenting <hi>thoſe Jealouſies,</hi> and <hi>Fears</hi> of the <hi>Beſt Church-men,</hi> and <hi>Greateſt Men</hi> in <hi>it,</hi> is not ſo eaſie to diſcover here: That they had ſome ſhare in <hi>them,</hi> is what we have very good reaſon to ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, ſince we are ſure that <hi>they</hi> did reap the greateſt advantage from <hi>them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But when <hi>that time</hi> was come which the <hi>Fanatical E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> ſaid the <hi>Church-men</hi> waited onely for: and when thoſe <hi>deluding</hi> and <hi>deluded People</hi> ſaw that to the Confuſion of all their falſe ſurmizes <hi>the Clergy</hi> of the <hi>Church of England</hi> continued <hi>firm</hi> to <hi>their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther-Church,</hi> and <hi>vigorous</hi> againſt all the <hi>Aſſaults</hi> of <hi>Rome;</hi> and were as far as ever from betraying the <hi>Cauſe</hi> or the <hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> or the <hi>Proteſtant Intereſt;</hi> thoſe <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies</hi> were laid aſide and buried; and the Multitude began to have a new as well as juſt appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion of things; and were not aſhamed to confeſs that <hi>they</hi> had been very much abuſed with thoſe <hi>falſe Fears,</hi> and <hi>groundleſs Jealouſies,</hi> and that <hi>they</hi> were now abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly convinced that the <hi>Church-men</hi> really <hi>were</hi> what they had all along profeſſed and ſhewn themſelves to <hi>be, True
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:49186:5"/>Sons of the Church of England,</hi> and the moſt <hi>faithful</hi> and <hi>diligent Defenders of the Proteſtant Cauſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This diſcovery of the <hi>Sincerity</hi> of the <hi>Clergy</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> was, I do not in the leaſt queſtion, very uneaſy to <hi>one Part</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> who could not but be highly troubled that the ſerviceable and proſperous <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies</hi> were now out of date, and laid by as utterly uſeleſs: and I do not doubt that they were there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon no little unwilling to have <hi>them</hi> quite forgotten.</p>
            <p>All the buſineſs was how to retrieve thoſe <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies</hi> before they were clean extinct: and what muſt be done to keep <hi>ſome</hi> of <hi>them</hi> up, and to continue them in the <hi>Heads</hi> of the <hi>deluded People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I can very eaſily ſuppoſe that there were as many <hi>Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients</hi> almoſt, as <hi>Welwiſhers</hi> to the <hi>ſupport</hi> of the <hi>Old Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod:</hi> but he in my opinion ſeems to have hit on the moſt probable means, who was for ſhewing to the World that there ſtill is an <hi>Agreement</hi> in <hi>moſt material things</hi> between the <hi>two Churchs</hi> of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This</hi> was the <hi>Invention</hi> of <hi>one</hi> of our <hi>Repreſenters Church,</hi> who it ſeems took it very ill that the world ſhould think the <hi>Clergy</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> were ſuch great <hi>Oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> or that they really were as far from being infected with <hi>Principles</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> as <hi>they</hi> were deſirous to be thought at <hi>this time.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That he might therefore convince the People, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to the world that <hi>great miſtake,</hi> He prepares a <hi>Collec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> and publiſhes in <hi>Print</hi> his worthy <hi>deſign,</hi> which was to ſhew according to the <hi>Title</hi> it bears, <hi>An Agreement be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Church of England and the Church of Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But there were <hi>two great Miſtakes</hi> committed in the publiſhing of that <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> which were like to ruin the deſign of it, and prevent its doing any good towards the keeping up of <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jealouſies</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Clergy:</hi>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:49186:5"/>the <hi>One</hi> was, that the <hi>Author</hi> thereof did diſcover ſo plainly <hi>what Church</hi> he was <hi>of,</hi> and <hi>the other</hi> was, that the <hi>Book</hi> did in its <hi>Title page</hi> ſhew out of <hi>whoſe Preſs</hi> it came.</p>
            <p>Had <hi>it</hi> been the <hi>Work</hi> of ſome <hi>Proteſtant Diſſenter,</hi> it would have required a fairer examination, and deſerved the greater credit, as coming from <hi>one</hi> who commonly makes ſuch profeſſions of <hi>Conſcience</hi> and <hi>Sincerity,</hi> and who (by his former ſhare of promoting <hi>Fears</hi> and <hi>Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſies</hi> of the <hi>Clergy</hi>) might ſeem to be in a <hi>particular manner</hi> intereſted to make good his <hi>quondam charge</hi> againſt the <hi>Clergy</hi> of the <hi>Church of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, had the <hi>Author</hi> but <hi>perſonated</hi> a <hi>Diſſenter in it,</hi> and publiſhed it as from <hi>one</hi> of <hi>that kind,</hi> it might have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected better ſucceſs. But for <hi>him</hi> to lay open ſo plainly <hi>himſelf,</hi> and to let the world know that <hi>he</hi> was of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and which was as ill managed, to have <hi>Henry Hills</hi> to ſet <hi>his name</hi> to <hi>his Book,</hi> that ſo every one might know whence it came; this was <hi>too groſs</hi> to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon any, and this was enough to blaſt the <hi>whole de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign,</hi> ſince there are no people of tolerable ſenſe but would as ſoon as they ſaw whence it came, reflect with <hi>them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,</hi> that <hi>this Book</hi> muſt needs be a <hi>ridiculous ſham,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe if there were in reality <hi>any ſuch Agreements</hi> between <hi>any</hi> of the <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> would have been far from being either <hi>ſo uncivil</hi> to their <hi>ſecret Friends,</hi> or ſo much <hi>Enemies</hi> to their <hi>own Deſigns,</hi> as to diſcover their <hi>private Allies</hi> to the world, and poſt them up that <hi>every Body</hi> may know <hi>them,</hi> and thereby deprive themſelves of ever hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſuch <hi>ſecret Friends</hi> any more.</p>
            <p>And therefore this <hi>ridiculous Pamphlet</hi> was ſo far from helping on, or keeping up the <hi>Jealouſie-Deſign,</hi> or doing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:49186:6"/>them any good <hi>that way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Dr. <hi>Sh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>lock.</hi>
               </note> that it onely ſerved to provoke that <hi>very worthy Perſon</hi> who was particularly aimd at and abuſed in it to publiſh a <hi>Vindication</hi> of <hi>himſelf,</hi> wherein he hath throughly baſted the <hi>pretences</hi> of <hi>his Romiſh Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> and broke the neck of the <hi>ſilly deſign.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ill fortune however of that <hi>fruitleſs deſign</hi> did not deter <hi>our Repreſenter</hi> from trying the <hi>ſame Method</hi> again; ſo good and ſo promiſing an undertaking muſt not be let fall for the <hi>miſcarriages of one Man;</hi> a deſign ſo neceſſary muſt be purſued, and care onely taken not to make any more ſuch <hi>falſe ſteps,</hi> as the <hi>former Author</hi> had, but to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure the <hi>Privacy</hi> of <hi>it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this good purpoſe our <hi>Repreſenter</hi> comes forth, and preſents the world with no fewer than <hi>ſixteen Articles</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> extracted out of <hi>one Book</hi> lately publiſhed by a <hi>Member</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England;</hi> and this in the <hi>diſguiſe</hi> of a <hi>Diſſenter,</hi> and without <hi>any Printers name</hi> to <hi>it,</hi> that ſo the <hi>Suppoſitious Brat</hi> might paſs <hi>undiſcovered,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> that was ſaid in this pretended <hi>Letter</hi> might be ſwallowed by the <hi>unthinking Multitude</hi> as if it came from <hi>ſome real Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>new Method</hi> the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> was pleaſed to try <hi>firſt</hi> againſt <hi>me;</hi> for out of <hi>my Anſwer</hi> to <hi>his Nubes Teſtium</hi> are all <hi>thoſe Articles</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> pretended to be collected, which are the <hi>Subject</hi> of that <hi>perſonating Letter</hi> from the <hi>Diſſenter to the Divines of the Church of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to the great diſparagement of our <hi>crafty Repreſenter, this Letter</hi> neither was ſo well managed as <hi>it</hi> ought to have been; for tho there was <hi>Art</hi> in fathering the <hi>Brat</hi> upon the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> as if it had come from <hi>One</hi> of <hi>them,</hi> yet <hi>this Art</hi> was forgotten, to <hi>perſonate the Diſſenter</hi> a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle better, for in this <hi>pretended Letter</hi> One plainly ſees the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> in <hi>every Period,</hi> and his <hi>own ſtile</hi> carried through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:49186:6"/>
            <p>And therefore, as tho the <hi>Author</hi> were conſcious to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and <hi>his Friends</hi> of the ſame mind, that <hi>his ſtile</hi> would endanger <hi>his diſcovery,</hi> all care was taken that <hi>it</hi> might not be known out of <hi>what Preſs</hi> this <hi>pretended Letter</hi> was ſent: <hi>Randal Taylor</hi> the <hi>Publiſher</hi> of it had a ſtrict charge laid upon <hi>him</hi> not to diſcover <hi>whence he</hi> had <hi>it,</hi> or for <hi>whom</hi> he did publiſh it, and thereupon durſt not tell <hi>whence he</hi> had it: and ſo reſolute were <hi>they</hi> to have it concealed, that when my <hi>Bookſellers Servant</hi> went the next day to <hi>Henry Hills Printing-houſe</hi> to buy <hi>two</hi> or <hi>three</hi> of the <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> among <hi>other Books, they</hi> denied the <hi>Letter,</hi> and refuſed to ſell <hi>him any</hi> of it, tho he <hi>ſaw</hi> and <hi>pointed</hi> to a <hi>heap</hi> of <hi>them</hi> in the <hi>ſhop</hi> before their faces.</p>
            <p>But all this <hi>fooliſh care</hi> was to no purpoſe, ſince <hi>Henry Hills Print</hi> is too well known to <hi>all Bookſellers,</hi> and the <hi>Repreſenters ſtile</hi> to <hi>all Scholars</hi> that have given themſelves the trouble of reading his frothy <hi>Pamphlets.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs that upon publiſhing <hi>my Anſwer</hi> to the <hi>Compiler of the Nubes Teſtium</hi> I did expect to meet with a great deal of ill uſage and ſlanders; I had in <hi>my Anſwer</hi> to that <hi>Book</hi> of the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> diſcovered <hi>two things</hi> in relation to the <hi>Author</hi> of <hi>it,</hi> which I knew would incenſe and gall the <hi>Author</hi> of <hi>it</hi> as much as they would pleaſe the <hi>Generality</hi> of <hi>Readers:</hi> the <hi>One</hi> was that <hi>He</hi> had <hi>ſtole</hi> his <hi>whole Book</hi> (except a ſmall paſſage or two) out of <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talis Alexandre,</hi> a preſent <hi>Writer</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> without <hi>once</hi> mentioning whence <hi>He</hi> had it: The <hi>other thing</hi> was, that <hi>He</hi> had ſtole the <hi>Book</hi> out of an <hi>Author, every one</hi> of <hi>whoſe Volumes</hi> made uſe of by this <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giary</hi> had been condemned to <hi>the flames</hi> two years <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore</hi> by the <hi>preſent Pope,</hi> and <hi>all people</hi> forbid, under <hi>pain</hi> of <hi>Excommunication immediately incurr'd,</hi> the <hi>keeping, reading</hi> or <hi>tranſcribing any of thoſe Volumes;</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:49186:7"/>ſtands <hi>excommunicate</hi> for his pains by the <hi>preſent Pope,</hi> and cannot <hi>be abſolved</hi> by <hi>any perſon</hi> but the <hi>Pope himſelf,</hi> or the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome for the time being.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Firſt</hi> of theſe did diſcover how much a <hi>Scholar</hi> our <hi>Repreſenter</hi> was notwithſtanding that <hi>Pompous Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> out of <hi>Fathers:</hi> and <hi>the other</hi> ſhewed as plainly, how <hi>dutiful</hi> a <hi>Son</hi> of <hi>the Church he</hi> is notwithſtanding all the <hi>fine things</hi> ſaid in behalf of the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>any</hi> of <hi>his Pieces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As I did expect, ſo I now have found that I have in the <hi>higheſt manner</hi> diſobliged our <hi>Repreſenting Compiler,</hi> ſince I meet with the <hi>worſt uſage</hi> that rage or malice were able to dictate. I little dreamed that in the mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering up of <hi>my faults</hi> and <hi>miſtakes, Popery</hi> would have been <hi>any part</hi> of my <hi>charge:</hi> but it ſeems I was ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly miſtaken; and tho I, who may be allowed to know my <hi>own ſenſe</hi> beſt, did believe there was <hi>no more Popery</hi> in my <hi>Book,</hi> than there is either in <hi>my Heart</hi> or <hi>my Head,</hi> yet this <hi>prying Repreſenter</hi> can find a <hi>great deal</hi> of <hi>it</hi> there, and charges me (quoting <hi>place</hi> and <hi>page</hi> for it) with <hi>ſixteen Articles</hi> of <hi>Popery;</hi> which <hi>large Bill</hi> againſt <hi>me</hi> I will now examine.</p>
            <div n="1-3" type="charge_and_reply">
               <p>The <hi>three firſt Articles</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> that I am charged with are <hi>about the Pope himſelf,</hi> in favour of <hi>whom</hi> I am charged with ſaying firſt <hi>that I can grant, that the Biſhop of Rome is the Succeſſor of S.</hi> Peter. 2. <hi>That that See is the Centre of the Catholick Communion, while poſſeſt by an Orthodox Biſhop. 3. That whoſoever ſeparates himſelf from it, profeſſing the true Faith, and poſſeſſed by a Catholick Biſhop, is guilty of Schiſm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And is <hi>this</hi> ingenuous dealing? muſt <hi>every Diſputant</hi> be charged with what he grants <hi>meerly</hi> for diſputation ſake? And muſt <hi>every Writer</hi> be charged with what he onely
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:49186:7"/>
                  <hi>ſuppoſes</hi> for argument ſake, and to <hi>expoſe</hi> his <hi>Adverſary</hi> more plainly? This is very hard and very unreaſonable mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to charge either <hi>Diſputant</hi> or <hi>Writer</hi> with <hi>teaching</hi> what he does onely <hi>grant</hi> for Argument ſake, and with <hi>believing</hi> what he meerly <hi>ſuppoſes</hi> for the ſame purpoſe: and yet <hi>this</hi> is my <hi>Caſe</hi> in that <hi>Accuſation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I was in that <hi>chapter</hi> of my <hi>Book</hi> out of <hi>which</hi> theſe <hi>paſſages</hi> are taken, ſhewing what a diſingenuous ſort of an <hi>Adverſary</hi> I had to deal with there; how <hi>he,</hi> when he came to treat of the <hi>Popes Supremacy,</hi> inſtead of put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting down a <hi>juſt</hi> and <hi>fair account</hi> of the <hi>Pretenſions</hi> of the <hi>Biſhops</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> did onely mention <hi>two</hi> or <hi>three</hi> trifling things which any one with adding onely to them two or three neceſſary words <hi>might grant,</hi> and yet be as far as any one ever was from believing the <hi>Supremacy</hi> of the <hi>Popes</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That I might therefore expoſe <hi>him,</hi> and ſhew the great looſeneſs and craft with which <hi>he</hi> wrote, I did in that place undertake to prove <hi>it</hi> in particular: and went through <hi>all</hi> the <hi>Heads</hi> of <hi>that chapter,</hi> ſtill telling <hi>him</hi> at every <hi>one</hi> of <hi>them</hi> that I <hi>could grant it,</hi> and yet continue <hi>without any obligation in the leaſt of believing the Popes Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What I had ſaid there, and granted as is uſual in all Writers, meerly for to expoſe my <hi>Adverſary,</hi> this <hi>Letter-Writer</hi> hath by ſleight of hand turned into honeſt confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and makes me <hi>aſſert</hi> in the <hi>Letter</hi> what I had onely <hi>ſuppoſed</hi> in the <hi>Book.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whoſoever will look into <hi>that page</hi> of <hi>my Book,</hi> will quickly ſee how extravagantly abuſive and falſe this charge in the <hi>Letter</hi> upon me is, and how very diſinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous and malicious that perſon muſt be that would from thence affix to me as an <hi>Aſſertion,</hi> about the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:49186:8"/>
                  <hi>Rome's Succeſſion</hi> and <hi>Unity,</hi> that which was onely a <hi>School-Conceſſion</hi> for <hi>Argument</hi> ſake.</p>
               <p>And tho this anſwer is ſufficient with all perſons of ſenſe to convince <hi>them</hi> what a <hi>Jugling Adverſary</hi> I have, yet there is <hi>an Expreſſion</hi> in that very <hi>paragraph,</hi> which does expreſs, as plainly as words can, my denyal of and disbelief of <hi>any</hi> of <hi>thoſe things</hi> that <hi>He</hi> lays to my charge in the <hi>Letter</hi> as fair <hi>Conceſſions</hi> of <hi>my Opinion</hi> about the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome:</hi> for immediately after <hi>thoſe paſſages</hi> ſet down in the <hi>Letter,</hi> I have theſe <hi>very words; I can, I ſay ſubſcribe</hi> (THOUGH I DO NOT) <hi>to all this without any Obligation in the leaſt of believing the Popes Supremacy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here I cannot but appeal to the world to judge betwixt <hi>me,</hi> and this <hi>Jugling Adverſary,</hi> whether any one could expreſs his meaning more plainly, and his diſſent more fully than I have done in <hi>that place,</hi> and whether that <hi>Adverſary</hi> muſt not be devoid of all Honeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Senſe or Conſcience that would notwithſtanding ſuch a <hi>direct denyal</hi> of <hi>mine</hi> expreſſed there, charge me with <hi>believing</hi> and <hi>granting</hi> that the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> is S. <hi>Peter's Succeſſor,</hi> that <hi>he is the Centre</hi> of <hi>Catholick Communion,</hi> and, that <hi>it is Schiſm to ſeparate from his See.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Had my <hi>ſtile</hi> been obſcure, and my <hi>expreſſions</hi> been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricate, and <hi>thoſe words,</hi> which did declare my direct diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief of thoſe things, at ſome great diſtance <hi>three</hi> or <hi>four pages</hi> off, for example, from <hi>thoſe</hi> quoted by the <hi>Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter;</hi> there might have been ſome ſmall pretence, ſome little colour for the knavery uſed here by <hi>him;</hi> but there was no ground for any <hi>ſuch Plea,</hi> for the <hi>Expreſſions</hi> and <hi>ſtile</hi> are plain enough there, and <hi>the words, <hi>though I do not</hi>
                  </hi> are in the <hi>very next line</hi> to his laſt <hi>quotation,</hi> and it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible but <hi>he</hi> ſhould both <hi>ſee them,</hi> and <hi>read them</hi> too.</p>
               <p>With what conſcience then could <hi>any man</hi> read <hi>thoſe
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:49186:8"/>words,</hi> and yet have the <hi>forehead</hi> from the very <hi>ſame page,</hi> to bring me in as believing the <hi>direct contrary.</hi> I am ſo far from thinking that any Chriſtian would be guilty of ſuch a deliberate and injurious impoſture, that I believe both <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Heathens</hi> would abhor and deteſt the being guilty of ſuch a <hi>malicious Forgery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for that <hi>good Opinion of the Pope,</hi> which this <hi>Jugler</hi> mentions afterwards in the <hi>Letter</hi> as <hi>mine,</hi> I think I have ſufficiently evidenced to the world in that <hi>ſecond Chapter</hi> of my <hi>Anſwer to the Compiler</hi> how little a <hi>Friend to,</hi> or <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourer</hi> of the <hi>Popes Pretenſions</hi> I am. If to ſhew that there is <hi>no ground</hi> or <hi>Authority from Scripture</hi> for his <hi>claims</hi> to <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy;</hi> if to ſhew that there is <hi>no ground</hi> for the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Supremacy</hi> from the <hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Canons</hi> of the <hi>Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Church for the firſt ſix hundred years</hi> after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and to back this with <hi>Three Challenges</hi> to <hi>all the Romiſh Prieſts</hi> in <hi>England</hi> to name <hi>one Canon</hi> in the <hi>Code</hi> of the <hi>Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Church</hi> that <hi>does</hi> either <hi>conſtitute,</hi> or <hi>aſſert,</hi> or <hi>ſuppoſe</hi> the <hi>Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome to be that Head</hi> and <hi>Supreme Paſtor</hi> of the <hi>Univerſal Church</hi> which <hi>their General Council</hi> of <hi>Flo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> defined <hi>him to be;</hi> if to ſhew I ſay all <hi>theſe things</hi> be a diſcovery of a <hi>mans good Opinion</hi> of the <hi>Pope,</hi> I do here own that I have as <hi>good an Opinion</hi> of the <hi>Pope</hi> as any <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> within the four Seas.</p>
               <p>But I am afraid that I never ſhall have either favour or thanks for my <hi>good Opinion of the Pope:</hi> And however the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> who I believe read <hi>that chapter</hi> thorough, does tell the world of his meeting with my <hi>good Opinion of the Pope</hi> in <hi>that Book;</hi> I am very fully perſuaded that <hi>he</hi> does no more believe <hi>himſelf</hi> that I have any <hi>good Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the Pope,</hi> than I believe that <hi>he</hi> is at this <hi>Inſtant</hi> in <hi>Japan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But when a mans hand is in at ſuch ſort of writing
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:49186:9"/>and when <hi>he</hi> is reſolved to <hi>blacken</hi> his <hi>Adverſary,</hi> but wants <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Ground</hi> for <hi>ſuch Calumnies,</hi> He muſt e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en do as my <hi>Adverſary</hi> does, <hi>invent</hi> himſelf what he would fain have <hi>found</hi> in his <hi>Adverſaries Work,</hi> and charge him with <hi>ſaying that</hi> in his <hi>Work</hi> which he <hi>does not,</hi> nay which he <hi>ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly denies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I think I have fully vindicated my ſelf from the <hi>charge</hi> about the <hi>Pope himſelf</hi> againſt <hi>me,</hi> and expoſed enough the <hi>notorius Calumny</hi> of the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> upon <hi>this Point:</hi> However, leſt any <hi>Reader</hi> ſhould not ſufficiently appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend the <hi>firſt part</hi> of my <hi>Anſwer</hi> to this <hi>Calumny,</hi> and leſt <hi>any</hi> of the <hi>Repreſenters Friends</hi> ſhould deny the <hi>Proof</hi> of the deliberate Falſification of my meaning, becauſe the <hi>paſſage</hi> is not ſet down, and they converſe commonly with <hi>thoſe</hi> who either have not, or will not, or it may be, muſt not look into <hi>my Book</hi> it ſelf, I will tranſcribe <hi>thoſe two</hi> whole <hi>paragraphs</hi> thence, which are the <hi>Subject</hi> of <hi>his Charge</hi> and <hi>my Anſwer,</hi> and <hi>they</hi> are <hi>theſe</hi> in the <hi>begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> of my <hi>Second Chapter concerning the Popes Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> p. 8.</p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">
                  <p>Our <hi>Compiler</hi> being now come to a Point of debate, doth not forget his art of <hi>palliating,</hi> which was ſo ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to him in his <hi>Miſrepreſentations</hi> and <hi>Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations</hi> of <hi>Popery. He</hi> cannot but know (and therefore ought to have avoided it) that this looſe talk about <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor of Peter,</hi> and <hi>Centre</hi> of <hi>Catholick Communion</hi> does not reach the <hi>Pretenſions</hi> of the <hi>Biſhops of Rome,</hi> nor fully and fairly declare what <hi>Power, Juriſdiction</hi> and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority,</hi> in and over the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> thoſe <hi>Biſhops</hi> challenge as <hi>their Right.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To let him ſee how looſely <hi>he</hi> manages <hi>this debate</hi>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:49186:9"/>betwixt <hi>us,</hi> I can with putting in two or three <hi>neceſſary words</hi> ſubſcribe to all our <hi>Compiler</hi> ſays for the <hi>Pope,</hi> and yet be as far from owning the <hi>Popes Supremacy,</hi> as the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England is</hi> or ever <hi>was. The Fathers teach,</hi> ſays our <hi>Compiler</hi>
                     <note n="(a)" place="margin">
                        <hi>Nubes Teſtium, p.</hi> 22.</note> 
                     <hi>that Chriſt Built his Church upon Peter:</hi> So ſay I too, if by <hi>Fathers</hi> here be meant two or three of <hi>them,</hi> and not the <hi>Fathers unanimouſly</hi> (as he hath it before) or <hi>generally. That the Biſhop of Rome is the Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor of Saint</hi> Peter, is what I can alſo grant, and <hi>that that See is the Centre of the Catholick Communion,</hi> if I may but put in here what is abſolutely neceſſary, <hi>while poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed by an Orthodox Biſhop,</hi> and <hi>that whoſoever ſeparates himſelf from it</hi> (I add, <hi>profeſſing the true Faith, and poſſeſſed by a Catholick Biſhop) is guilty of Schiſm.</hi> I CAN, I SAY, SUBSCRIBE (THOUGH I DO NOT) TO ALL This, without any Obligation in the leaſt of believing the <hi>Popes Supremacy:</hi> All that our <hi>Compiler</hi> puts down here, reaching no farther than a <hi>Primacy</hi> of <hi>Order,</hi> does not at all ſuppoſe in the <hi>Popes</hi> any <hi>Jurisdiction</hi> or <hi>Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> over the <hi>Catholick Church.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="charge_and_reply">
               <p>Having diſpatched my <hi>Vindication</hi> againſt the <hi>Charge</hi> of the <hi>three firſt Articles</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> I come now to examine the <hi>fourth,</hi> which doth charge me with <hi>doubting whether there be really any Controverſy about Tradition, betwixt the Church of Rome and the Church of England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well then, are theſe <hi>my expreſſions</hi> in the <hi>place quoted?</hi> Or is <hi>this</hi> the ſenſe of <hi>them</hi> there? I muſt profeſs to the world that had I not already diſcovered the cheats of the <hi>malicious Repreſenter</hi> in the <hi>former Articles,</hi> I could not have believed that <hi>any</hi> perſon of common ſenſe or learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing would have been guilty of ſuch tricks.</p>
               <p>I had the ſame occaſion in <hi>my chapter</hi> about the <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:49186:10"/>that I had in the <hi>former chapter</hi> about <hi>Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy,</hi> of ſhewing how looſe a <hi>Writer</hi> our <hi>Compiler</hi> is, and expoſing <hi>him</hi> for putting that down as an <hi>account</hi> of the <hi>Controverſy</hi> which I could ſubſcribe to, if taken in <hi>that ſenſe</hi> which the words would fairly bear, and yet be never the nearer to <hi>Popery</hi> than I <hi>now</hi> am, or ever intend to <hi>be.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon this, coming to examine what he had put down at the <hi>Head</hi> of <hi>his Collections</hi> about <hi>Tradition,</hi> I have <hi>theſe expreſſions;</hi>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">To ſtate therefore the <hi>Controverſy</hi> about <hi>Tradition</hi> (if there really be <hi>any</hi>) betwixt <hi>us,</hi> he ſhould not have put down <hi>that</hi> for the account of the <hi>debate</hi> herein betwixt us, which is agreed to by <hi>both ſides,</hi> nor ſhould have omitted <hi>that</hi> wherein WE REAL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LY DISAGREE, and <hi>that</hi> is about <hi>the Scriptures be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a certain and Perfect Rule of Faith</hi> WITHOUT THE HELP of TRADITION, which the <hi>Council</hi> of <hi>Trent</hi> hath made to be of <hi>Equal Authority</hi> with the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>One would think ſuch clear expreſſions as theſe would have prevented my being accuſed of <hi>doubting whether there really be any Controverſie about Tradition betwixt the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>and the Church of</hi> England, but no clearneſs it ſeems can be protection againſt the <hi>Malice</hi> of ſuch an <hi>Adverſary</hi> as is fallen upon <hi>me:</hi> and therefore <hi>he</hi> puts down <hi>thoſe expreſſions</hi> as <hi>mine doubting, whether there be really any Controverſie about Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition betwixt the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>and the Church of</hi> England; when in <hi>that very paragraph</hi> I ſay that <hi>We</hi> (meaning the <hi>Churches</hi> of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Rome) Really Diſagree</hi> about <hi>Tradition's being part of the Rule of Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And therefore any other Reader, leſs ſpiteful than my angry <hi>Adverſary,</hi> would eaſily have ſeen and obſerved that the <hi>expreſſion</hi> in the <hi>beginning</hi> of the <hi>paragraph (if
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:49186:10"/>there really be any)</hi> was uſed and intended for an alluſion to <hi>that ſtate</hi> of the <hi>Controverſie</hi> which had been ſet down by the <hi>Compiler</hi> about <hi>Tradition,</hi> and ought not to be wire-drawn to make me <hi>doubt that</hi> in the beginning of the <hi>paragraph,</hi> the <hi>contrary</hi> to <hi>which</hi> I did directly <hi>aſſert</hi> within <hi>three lines</hi> after.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5-6" type="charge_and_reply">
               <p>The fifth Article of the charge againſt me is, that I did ſay <hi>that the Tradition of the Catholick Church is to be received;</hi> and the <hi>ſixth</hi> is of the ſame kind, that I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed there, <hi>That by Tradition we receive the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and know how to ſeparate the Scriptures from Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cryphal or Suppoſitious Writings.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do freely own that <hi>theſe</hi> are <hi>my expreſſions</hi> in <hi>that place,</hi> and theſe I am ſure are far from looking like <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,</hi> if I that wrote <hi>them</hi> may be allowed to tell in what ſenſe I did mean and intend <hi>them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All the ſervice that my <hi>Adverſary</hi> could expect from the citing and inſiſting upon <hi>them</hi> was onely to amuſe the <hi>common Readers</hi> with the <hi>Word Tradition,</hi> that they not underſtanding the <hi>Ambiguity</hi> of the <hi>Word,</hi> nor in what ſeveral ſenſes the <hi>Word Tradition</hi> was uſed, might be tempted to believe that I was for ſetting up there <hi>that Tradition</hi> which they uſed to hear preached againſt ſo much by the <hi>Clergy</hi> of the <hi>Church of England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By <hi>Tradition</hi> here which I ſaid <hi>we receive</hi> or admit of, I did not mean <hi>that Tradition</hi> which is ſet up as <hi>part</hi> of <hi>the Rule of Faith</hi> in the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> nor did I any more mean <hi>Tradition</hi> as it is taken for <hi>any Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> which they ſay was from the beginning delivered to them. All that I meant by <hi>Tradition</hi> there was no more than the <hi>bare means</hi> of <hi>delivering down to us the Word of God,</hi> and any <hi>Rites</hi> or <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> in the <hi>Ancient Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:49186:11"/>
               <p>When I ſaid therefore that <hi>by this Tradition we recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Holy Scriptures, and know how to ſeparate the Scriptures from Apocryphal or Suppoſititious Writings:</hi> The full and clear meaning of thoſe expreſſions was, that the <hi>Canonical Books</hi> of the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> or (to ſpeak to the meaneſt capacity) that the <hi>Bible</hi> was delivered down from time to time, and from hand to hand in all Ages unto <hi>us,</hi> that <hi>we</hi> did receive <hi>them</hi> from our <hi>Forefathers</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> as they had received them from <hi>theirs</hi> up unto the beginning, and that ſince they delivered down to us onely thoſe Books, which the <hi>Church of England</hi> does believe and admit for the <hi>Word of God,</hi> we do thereby know that <hi>no other Books</hi> could be <hi>part</hi> of the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> which were not handed down to us for <hi>ſuch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is as much as I need to offer either in <hi>Vindication</hi> of my ſelf, or <hi>explication</hi> of my <hi>words,</hi> when I ſpoke of <hi>Tradition;</hi> but becauſe I cannot clear my innocence too much herein, I will ſhew the world that I had very good <hi>Vouchers</hi> for <hi>every word</hi> that I ſaid thereabout, and will produce the <hi>ſenſe</hi> of <hi>Arch-Biſhop Uſher,</hi> who never was thought by <hi>any Sort</hi> of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to be any ways incline<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to, or guilty of <hi>Popery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>moſt learned Prelate</hi> in his <hi>Reply</hi> to the <hi>Jeſuits Challenge</hi> hath theſe words about
<note n="(b)" place="margin">p. 35.</note> 
                  <hi>Tradition.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">This muſt I needs tell you before we begin, that you much miſtake the matter, if you think that Traditions of all ſorts promiſcuouſly are ſtruck at by our Religion. We willingly acknowledge, that the word of God which by ſome of the Apoſtles was ſet down in writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, was both by themſelves, and others of their
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:49186:11"/>fellow-labourers, delivered by word of mouth: and that the Church in ſucceeding ages was bound not only to preſerve thoſe ſacred writings committed to her truſt, but alſo to deliver unto her children <hi>vivâ voce</hi> the form of wholſome words contained therein. Traditions therefore of this nature, come not within the compaſs of our controverſy: the queſtion being betwixt us <hi>de ipſâ Doctrinâ traditâ,</hi> not <hi>de tradendi modo;</hi> touching the ſubſtance of the doctrine delivered, not of the manner of delivering it. Again, it muſt be remembred that here we ſpeak of doctrine deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as <hi>the word of God,</hi> that is, of points of religion revealed unto the Prophets and Apoſtles, for the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual information of Gods people: not of rites and ceremonies, and other ordinances which are left to the diſpoſition of the Church, and conſequently be not of <hi>divine</hi> but of <hi>poſitive</hi> and <hi>humane</hi> right. Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions therefore of this kind likewiſe are not properly brought within the circuit of this queſtion.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus that <hi>moſt learned Man,</hi> whoſe Authority is ſo deſervedly great in the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="charge_and_reply">
               <p>The <hi>Seventh Article</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> is, that I ſaid there, that I was <hi>willing and ready to receive any Doctrine not written that hath as</hi> perpetual, unanimous, and certain a Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition <hi>as the</hi> Scripture; <hi>and that I onely wait for the proving this, and then I am ready to embrace all the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines of Popery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for thoſe laſt words, <hi>and then he is ready to embrace all the Doctrines of Popery,</hi> which are maliciouſly put in the <hi>Italick Character,</hi> that ſo they might be thought by the <hi>Reader</hi> to be my own words, I have no <hi>ſuch expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions</hi> there, and <hi>theſe</hi> are onely the <hi>Repreſenter</hi>'s conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:49186:12"/>draw from what I had ſaid there, <hi>that we onely wait for their proving that</hi> any <hi>of</hi> thoſe Doctrines <hi>they would obtrude upon us have been</hi> thus univerſally deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered.</p>
               <p>But his buſineſs here was to make the paſſage look as invidious as he could, and therefore he was ſo very care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to put his own <hi>Conſequence</hi> down in the moſt odious terms that <hi>he</hi> could deviſe.</p>
               <p>The <hi>former part</hi> of the <hi>Accuſation</hi> about my profeſſed readineſs <hi>to receive any Doctrine not written that hath as perpetual, unanimous and certain a Tradition as the Doctrines written in Scripture have,</hi> I do readily own, and plead guilty unto it, ſince I am very well ſatisfied that <hi>my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> as a <hi>Member</hi> of the <hi>Church of England</hi> is not in danger of being ſhockt or endangered by it. I do ſtill ſay, that I am now <hi>ready to receive any ſuch unwritten Doctrines;</hi> which <hi>expreſſions</hi> of mine, as well in my <hi>Book</hi> as <hi>here,</hi> are far from ſuppoſing that the <hi>Church of England</hi> wants any <hi>neceſſary means</hi> of <hi>Salvation,</hi> or that there are in any <hi>other Church</hi> any ſuch <hi>unwritten Doctrines</hi> ſo qualified for a <hi>Chriſtian's Reception</hi> as I there require; but <hi>they</hi> do on the contrary ſuppoſe that the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> is not able to ſhew for any <hi>one point of Religion</hi> which they would obtrude upon us ſuch a <hi>perpetual, una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous</hi> and <hi>certain Tradition</hi> as I do demand for <hi>it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I uſed thoſe words there, becauſe I did not onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, but was fully perſuaded that it is impoſſible for the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> to prove in that Method any of <hi>their Doctrines</hi> which are refuſed by us; and if it be impoſſible, I ſuppoſe I am in no very great likelihood of ever becoming a <hi>Roman Catholick,</hi> while I make a thing impoſſible to them the condition of my ever becoming a member of <hi>their Church.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="charge_and_reply">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:49186:12"/>
               <p>The <hi>eighth Article</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> is my ſaying that <hi>there is no neceſſity of Expreſs Scripture for the Conſtitutions and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, which his Church enjoyns in order to the more regular and decent ſervice of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But how comes this to be an <hi>Article</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> againſt me? And how comes this to be chriſtened <hi>Popery?</hi> Hath it not always been the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Reformed Church</hi> of <hi>England?</hi> Is not this a <hi>Doctrine</hi> common to all <hi>perſuaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of <hi>Chriſtians</hi> in the world? I cannot but look upon the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> in great pain and concern to muſter up a <hi>ſet</hi> of <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> againſt me, that is forced to make a falſe muſter, and to call that <hi>Popery</hi> which in rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity is <hi>not.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>His weakneſs is as viſible as his malice in <hi>this affair;</hi> as his malice put him upon making me odious by draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up a charge of <hi>Popiſh Principles</hi> againſt me, ſo his weakneſs did in this place betray him into a miſcalling that Doctrine <hi>Popery,</hi> which is <hi>common</hi> to <hi>all ſorts</hi> of <hi>Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> hath profeſſed <hi>this</hi> as her ſenſe all along, that <hi>there is no neceſſity of Expreſs Scripture</hi> for <hi>her Conſtitutions</hi> and <hi>Orders for the more regular and decent Service of God,</hi> but that theſe things are commanded one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in general, and the particular <hi>determination</hi> thereof left to the <hi>Governours</hi> of the <hi>ſeveral Churches.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor is the <hi>Church of England</hi> alone, nor the <hi>onely Church</hi> among the <hi>Reformed</hi> of this perſuaſion; the <hi>Reformed Churches</hi> beyond the Seas do altogether concur with <hi>Her</hi> in <hi>this;</hi> and ſo do all the <hi>Greek, Eaſtern</hi> and <hi>Southern Churches,</hi> not <hi>one</hi> of <hi>which</hi> doth require <hi>expreſs Texts</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> for the <hi>ſeveral Ceremonies</hi> and <hi>Conſtitutions</hi> in <hi>their Churches,</hi> for the <hi>more decent ſervice of God,</hi> but
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:49186:13"/>look upon a general Commiſſion to the <hi>Church</hi> from the <hi>Word of God</hi> to enable and empower them to provide and order the <hi>particular Modes</hi> and <hi>Practices.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay, our <hi>Diſſenters</hi> themſelves, notwithſtanding their too great rigidneſs in many things, cannot but ſubſcribe the <hi>Doctrine</hi> I ſet down above, ſince <hi>they</hi> do not pretend to ſhew <hi>expreſs Scripture</hi> for the ſeveral Orders made among <hi>them</hi> in relation to the <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of <hi>Time, Place, Poſtures</hi> and <hi>Geſtures</hi> uſed in the <hi>Service</hi> of <hi>God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Since then what I ſaid above, and was accuſed of <hi>Popery</hi> for it, proves to be a <hi>Doctrine</hi> equally eſpouſed by <hi>all Perſuaſions</hi> of <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> as well as by the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> I would fain know by what Art this is to be made <hi>Popery;</hi> we may as well, and with as great reaſon call the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of the <hi>Incarnation,</hi> or of the <hi>Reſurrection</hi> of our bleſſed <hi>Saviour Popery,</hi> as that <hi>Doctrine</hi> about the <hi>no neceſſity</hi> of <hi>expreſs Scripture</hi> for <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> ſince <hi>they</hi> are no more the <hi>general Belief</hi> of <hi>all Chriſtians</hi> than <hi>this</hi> laſt mentioned <hi>Doctrine</hi> is.</p>
               <p>This Charge then ought to have been omitted, ſince what I have ſaid above is ſo far from being <hi>one</hi> of <hi>my Articles</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> that it is <hi>no Popery at all,</hi> but a <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> aſſented to by the <hi>generality</hi> of the <hi>Chriſtian World.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>Before I go on to the <hi>next Article,</hi> I muſt conſider what he hath further to object againſt me in <hi>this Point.</hi> Here I am accuſed as if I had ſpoken onely my <hi>own ſenſe,</hi> and thereby given occaſion to my Adverſary to poſt me up as a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> or <hi>Popiſhly inclined</hi> for it, whereas I ſaid plainly, that it was the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>our Church,</hi> that <hi>there is no neceſſity</hi> of <hi>expreſs Scripture for the Conſtitutions and Practices which ſhe enjoyns in order to the more regular and decent ſervice of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:49186:13"/>
                  <p>But before my <hi>Adverſary</hi> ends his <hi>Letter,</hi> I am brought in again, as if I had ſaid that we eſpouſe a <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition which authoriſes Conſtitutions and Practices without any Authority of the Written Word:</hi> but I would fain know where it was that I ſaid <hi>this.</hi> I ſaid the <hi>Church</hi> taught that <hi>there was no neceſſity of Expreſs Scripture,</hi> and here it is come to <hi>no Scripture at all,</hi> for that is the place the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> alludes to.</p>
                  <p>I muſt therefore ask him ſeriouſly whether theſe two be the ſame, and whether there is no difference between <hi>not expreſs Scripture,</hi> and <hi>no Scripture at all:</hi> could this <hi>Adverſary</hi> ſhew that there is <hi>no medium</hi> betwixt <hi>Expreſs Scripture</hi> and <hi>no Scripture at all,</hi> it would have ſerved for ſome excuſe for him; but ſince that is impoſſible to be ſhewn, all people owning that <hi>what</hi> is onely implyed, or ordered in general terms, or may be deduced by ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional conſequence <hi>thence,</hi> is ſaid to be founded on <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> and to have the <hi>authority thereof,</hi> as well as <hi>that Doctrine</hi> which is delivered the moſt plainly or expreſly <hi>there,</hi> I muſt accuſe my <hi>Adverſary</hi> of very great diſinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity here, who does ſo injuriouſly turn the <hi>not requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring expreſs Scripture</hi> into the <hi>not requiring any Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Malice it ſeems will put men that are ſet upon revenge on doing the moſt unlawful things, and quite pervert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the words of their <hi>Adverſary,</hi> and making them ſay what they never did, nor thought on, the <hi>Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> otherwiſe could not but have ſeen how great a wrong he was doing me there, and his <hi>Conſcience</hi> muſt have upbraided him with a deliberate abuſing and perverting <hi>my words:</hi> but againſt <hi>that home-enemy</hi> he ſeems to be provided with <hi>armour</hi> of <hi>Proof.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="charge_and_reply">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:49186:14"/>
               <p>The <hi>next Article</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> laid to my charge is for aſſerting, <hi>That the Tradition of Antiquity is highly uſeful and neceſſary for the Interpretation of Points of Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I cannot ſee how <hi>this</hi> comes to be <hi>Popery</hi> any more than the <hi>laſt Article</hi> that I was charged with: my <hi>Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> buſineſs here ſeems to be only to amuſe the <hi>Multitude</hi> with the word <hi>Tradition;</hi> and therefore my care needs onely be employed for the acquitting of <hi>my</hi> ſelf to let the world ſee all that I or others mean by the <hi>Tradition</hi> mentioned here.</p>
               <p>By <hi>Tradition</hi> here I meant nothing elſe than <hi>thoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretations</hi> of <hi>difficult places</hi> of <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and <hi>explications</hi> of <hi>points</hi> of <hi>Faith</hi> which we meet with in the <hi>Fathers</hi> from the <hi>firſt Century</hi> downwards. Such <hi>Interpretations,</hi> whether received from <hi>thoſe</hi> before <hi>them,</hi> or found out by their own induſtry, and comparing of <hi>one part</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> with another, we do embrace as tranſmitted from <hi>them</hi> unto us in <hi>their Writings,</hi> and look upon ſuch Interpretations as very <hi>good Guides,</hi> and <hi>neceſſary Aſſiſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> to prevent our falling into <hi>Error,</hi> by letting us ſee how from time to time ſuch a <hi>Point</hi> of <hi>Doctrine,</hi> or <hi>ſuch a Text</hi> was taken by the <hi>generality,</hi> or <hi>unanimous Conſent</hi> of <hi>Fathers</hi> in ſuch a <hi>determinate ſenſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We have very great reaſon to value the <hi>Fathers</hi> upon this very account, becauſe <hi>they</hi> afford us <hi>ſuch evidences</hi> againſt <hi>thoſe Doctrines</hi> the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> would obtrude upon <hi>us:</hi> It cannot but be very great pleaſure to find that the <hi>Texts</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> which are alledged by the <hi>Romiſh Writers</hi> for <hi>ſome</hi> of their <hi>particular Doctrines</hi> are interpreted generally in a ſenſe quite contrary by the <hi>Primitive Fathers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am ſure that the <hi>Texts</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> alledged for that <hi>great fundamental Article</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> the <hi>Pope's Supremacy,</hi>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:49186:14"/>by the <hi>Romiſh Writers,</hi> are interpreted by the <hi>generality,</hi> and almoſt <hi>unanimous Conſent</hi> of the <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical Writers</hi> in a ſenſe quite contrary to <hi>that</hi> which the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> urge <hi>them</hi> for.</p>
               <p>I am very well aſſured that in very many <hi>other Points</hi> of <hi>Doctrine</hi> we are able to ſhew that the <hi>Generality</hi> of <hi>Fathers</hi> did not interpret the <hi>Texts</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> upon which the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> found them, in <hi>that ſenſe</hi> which they contend for; and I do believe that we may extend it to <hi>all points</hi> of <hi>Doctrine</hi> grounded upon <hi>Texts</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> which are under debate betwixt the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it be <hi>Popery</hi> then to value and embrace <hi>thoſe Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations</hi> which are delivered to us from the <hi>Fathers,</hi> and which are the <hi>Beſt Evidences</hi> next to the <hi>Holy Scriptures themſelves</hi> of the falſhood and unreaſonableneſs of the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Points</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> and which will aſſiſt us to ruin thoſe <hi>groundleſs Doctrines,</hi> I am content to be a <hi>Papiſt</hi> in <hi>this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle,</hi> but am affraid I ſhall never be looked upon as one jot more a <hi>Catholick</hi> for it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="charge_and_reply">
               <p>I will paſs on to the <hi>next</hi> charge, the <hi>Tenth Article</hi> of <hi>my Popery,</hi> which in my <hi>Adverſaries Letter</hi> runs thus, that <hi>He Honours the Saints</hi> in <hi>obſerving days in honour of them:</hi> But how comes it to be here, <hi>He honours,</hi> when I ſaid plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enough that WE, that is the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> do it? If there be any <hi>Popery</hi> in this charge, why is it laid to me as if I were delivering there onely my own Judgment or Practice, and not to the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> whom I ſpoke of expreſly there?</p>
               <p>But the Man begins to draw low, and to be put to all his Shifts to make up a Catalogue of Popery againſt me, that might make ſome ſhow, and therefore ſince I proved
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:49186:15"/>ſo ill natured in the reſt of my Book as to give him no advantage againſt me, He very wiſely charges that as my own, and an Article of my Popery, which is the avowed and moſt known Practice of the beſt Reformed Churches in the World.</p>
               <p>It is very well known that not onely the <hi>Church of England,</hi> but the beſt <hi>Reformed Churches</hi> abroad do ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve dayes in honour or memory of the Saints departed, who do at the ſame time deteſt and abhor the putting up of prayers unto them, or praying to them for to be made <hi>partakers of their Merits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He that will take the pains to look into the Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> may quickly ſee what <hi>honour</hi> it is that our <hi>Church</hi> payes to the <hi>Saints;</hi> that it is no other, nor no more than to Bleſs God for his mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Gifts and Graces unto them, whereby they were enabled to be glorious Examples of Holineſs to the World, and ſtrengthened in any Troubles or Fiery Trials to paſs through them with a Chriſtian Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Reſignation; and to pray unto <hi>him</hi> that we <hi>may have Grace to direct our Lives after their good Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is all that our <hi>Church</hi> doth practice in her <hi>Liturgy,</hi> and all that ſhe requires in the <hi>Sermons</hi> on thoſe <hi>Feſtival Days</hi> is, that the <hi>Example</hi> of the Servants of God, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly of that Saint whoſe memory is celebrated that day, may be ſet forth in the beſt manner, that ſo the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation may be perſuaded to direct their Lives alſo in the ſame good and holy paths.</p>
               <p>But tho this be all that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> doth practiſe or allow, yet He is for proving that I am for doing more; He ſays that I <hi>ſeem to grant all that is produced in Nubes Teſtium upon that Subject, one</hi> of <hi>whoſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:49186:15"/>Inſtances</hi> was their <hi>celebrating the Saints Memory with a Religious Solemnity, ſo to be Partakers of their Merits.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This charge I can anſwer in a very few words, that I neither did grant all he collected in the <hi>Nubes Teſtium</hi> upon that <hi>Subject,</hi> nor ſeemed to grant it: And which is more, that I could not, ſince I do not believe that the moſt Holy Men have <hi>any Merits,</hi> or that if they had, that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers can after their deceaſe be either helped by them, or be made Partakers of them by celebrating their Memories even with the moſt Religious Solemnity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="charge_and_reply">
               <p>The next Article of Popery is ſo very ridiculous, that it is not worth the putting down, or giving one word of Anſwer to it; but I muſt not omit it, leſt I be upbraid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and told that I had the cunning to ſlip over thoſe points which would diſcover me moſt, and lay me open to the world.</p>
               <p>It ſhall not then be put out of its place, or thrown quite away, but ſhall have its turn. In this <hi>Eleventh Article</hi> I am accuſed of ſaying, <hi>that it is generally piouſly believed, that the glorified Saints do intercede for the Church Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I would fain know what all this is to me, am I to be the Generality of Chriſtians? Or am I to anſwer for what other people believe? I ſpeak there of a General Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief, and have not put down one Syllable of my own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaſion herein, and yet this diſingenuous Adverſary is for fixing all this upon me, and puts it down as my own Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, or to no purpoſe at all. If he puts it down for my perſuaſion, he plays falſe ſince I do not hint one ſyllable of my ſenſe about it, and if it be as it really is to no purpoſe there, it is very ridiculous, and ought to be contemned as ſuch, and the Author of it for his Pains.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="charge_and_reply">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:49186:16"/>
               <p>The <hi>twelvth Article is</hi> that I ſhould ſay <hi>that the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour which in Primitive times was paid to the Memories of Saints, was nothing but what was highly juſt, and that herein they are imitated by us, as well as by any other Chriſtians,</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do own that theſe are my own expreſſions, or my ſenſe if by <hi>Primitive times</hi> be intended onely the Three firſt Centuries of the Church, of whoſe Ages I there ſpoke: but how comes this Article over again? this is the very ſame with the Tenth Article, and hath been ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently anſwered there, when I ſhewed what honour it was that our Church did pay unto the Memories of the Saints.</p>
               <p>But this Scarcity of matter is a troubleſom thing, and therefore the poor man is forced to come with the Old Article over again: but tho he be ſo impertinent with his ſecond Edition of the Article, I will not be ſo in tranſcribing my Anſwer to that 10th Article hither.</p>
               <p>I could however be almoſt willing to ſhew how all that the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> practiſes and requires as to the Memories of Saints is the very ſame that was prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed, nay all that was practiſed by the Primitive Chriſtians in the three firſt Centuries; but ſince this would take up much more room than I can afford it here, I will onely mention that famous Inſtance of the Church of <hi>Smyrna,</hi> how they were reſolved to Comme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morate their Martyred Biſhop S. <hi>Polycarp.</hi> As for worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, much leſs his Reliques, or of praying to him (as an old tranſlation of that Churches Epiſtle hath it) They inform the Chriſtians of <hi>Lyons</hi> and the whole world that they did deteſt the doing or thoughts of it, that they onely loved his Memory for that very great good will which he had ſhewn to his heavenly King and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:49186:16"/>and therefore did reſolve to celebrate with Joy and Praiſes the Birth-day (as the Church did then call the day of Martyrdom) of this Saint in Memory of him, and ſuch as had finiſhed their courſes like him, and for an incitement, and preparation to all that were to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate in ſuch bloudy encounters.</p>
               <p>Here is no mention either of Hymns or Prayers offered up to the Saint himſelf, and reaſon good, ſince theſe were then and long after, and ought always to be looked on as Peculiar to the God of Heaven alone.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="charge_and_reply">
               <p>The <hi>thirteenth Article</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> is that I ſay, <hi>that the Fathers kept the Reliques of Saints with reſpect and Venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and believed that God often wrought Miracles by them, and that they might do it too.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> hath drawn up the <hi>Charge,</hi> and this he hath done very like himſelf, that is, with more ſleight and cunning than any Honeſt perſon would uſe. For <hi>firſt,</hi> he puts down as <hi>my words, that the Fathers kept the Reliques of Saints with Reſpect and Veneration, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that God often wrought Miracles by them,</hi> whereas they are <hi>not my words,</hi> but <hi>his own,</hi> he had ſaid <hi>them</hi> in the <hi>Nubes Teſtium,</hi> and I did grant <hi>them,</hi> that ſo I might the better ſhew, that granting ſuch things were done then; this did not defend or countenance the <hi>preſent Practices</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome</hi> towards <hi>Reliques.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>However for that my granting and allowing of <hi>them,</hi> he hath made them <hi>mine,</hi> whereas had any other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of Senſe or Conſcience been to have mentioned <hi>thoſe Expreſſions,</hi> he would have put them down as <hi>ſaid</hi> by the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> himſelf, and <hi>
                     <hi>only</hi> granted</hi> by <hi>me.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>He next lays the charge as if I had ſaid that <hi>the Fathers</hi> indefinitely <hi>kept the Reliques of Saints;</hi> and by this the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:49186:17"/>
                  <hi>Reader</hi> muſt underſtand, if he pleaſes, that I ſaid that <hi>the Fathers</hi> in <hi>general</hi> did it, even the <hi>firſt Fathers</hi> of the <hi>three firſt Centuries,</hi> but this is as diſingenuous as the <hi>reſt</hi> of his <hi>Accuſations;</hi> for when I did grant his ſaying that the <hi>Fathers kept the Reliques,</hi> I did not grant it of the <hi>Fathers</hi> indefinitely, but did <hi>particularly</hi> ſpecifie what <hi>Fathers Practice</hi> I granted <hi>it</hi> to be, and did limit <hi>it</hi> to the <hi>Fathers</hi> of the <hi>latter Ages,</hi> by which I mean the <hi>latter end</hi> of the <hi>fourth,</hi> and the <hi>fifth,</hi> and <hi>following Centuries,</hi> as any one that will but peruſe <hi>that one page</hi> (out of which <hi>it</hi> is quoted) muſt neceſſarily ſee.</p>
               <p>As to the <hi>Charge</hi> then taken all together, I had ſo fully expreſſed my Senſe and my Mind in <hi>that Chapter</hi> that he carps at, that I think I need to uſe no other words to clear my ſelf and anſwer the <hi>Charge</hi> of <hi>Popery,</hi> than thoſe I had put down in that place.</p>
               <p>Speaking in <hi>that Chapter</hi> of the great <hi>difference</hi> betwixt <hi>what</hi> was practiſed in the <hi>fourth</hi> and <hi>fifth Centuries</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> in relation to <hi>Reliques,</hi> and <hi>what</hi> is practiſed now by the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> I have theſe words.
<q rend="margQuotes">I need not examine by retail <hi>his Teſtimonies</hi> from the <hi>latter end</hi> of the <hi>fourth</hi> and <hi>ſifth Centuries,</hi> the <hi>deſign</hi> of which <hi>he himſelf</hi> makes only to prove <hi>that the Fathers kept the Reliques of Saints with Reſpect and Veneration, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved that God often wrought Miracles by them:</hi> which WE <hi>do grant</hi> the Fathers of <hi>thoſe latter Ages</hi> did, and might do it too, as long as <hi>they</hi> kept (as <hi>they</hi> ſaid of <hi>themſelves</hi> that <hi>they always did)</hi> from <hi>paying Religious Worſhip</hi> unto <hi>them:</hi> But we ſay withal, that <hi>what</hi> the <hi>Chriſtians of thoſe Ages</hi> did about <hi>theſe things,</hi> does no ways defend the <hi>preſent Extravagancies</hi> of the <hi>Church of Rome;</hi> the <hi>Exceſſes</hi> wherein about <hi>Reliques</hi> are come
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:49186:17"/>to that <hi>ſcandalous height,</hi> as to make the <hi>learned</hi> men of their own Church aſhamed of them.</q>
               </p>
               <p>They that will compare <hi>this paſſage</hi> with the <hi>Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter's Extracts</hi> out of <hi>it</hi> in the 13th <hi>Article</hi> againſt me, cannot but diſcover what uſage every one muſt expect that dares to provoke ſo very angry a man.</p>
               <p>But that I may alſo ſhew my <hi>own Judgment</hi> about <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques,</hi> I will trouble the <hi>Reader</hi> with the <hi>next paragraph,</hi> wherein if I did not ſet down exactly (as I deſigned) the <hi>Opinion</hi> of our <hi>Mother-Church</hi> of <hi>England</hi> about thoſe things, yet I am ſure I did that of my own Soul.</p>
               <p>
                  <q rend="margQuotes">As to the <hi>Practice</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> which inquires not <hi>after,</hi> nor is ſolicitous <hi>about</hi> the <hi>Reliques</hi> of <hi>Saints,</hi> this may be ſaid in <hi>her defence,</hi> that <hi>ſhe</hi> finds <hi>no Practice</hi> or <hi>Command</hi> about <hi>any ſuch ſearching</hi> after the <hi>bones</hi> of the <hi>Dead</hi> in <hi>any part</hi> of <hi>Scripture</hi> of either Teſtament, but that their <hi>whole care</hi> then was to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit <hi>them</hi> to <hi>their Sepulchres</hi> in hopes of a <hi>future Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection,</hi> and never to diſturb <hi>their Aſhes;</hi> and therefore <hi>ſhe</hi> thinks it muſt needs be her <hi>greateſt commendation,</hi> that <hi>ſhe</hi> is more careful to imitate <hi>what</hi> ſhe finds <hi>writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi> and <hi>practiſed</hi> in the <hi>Scriptures themſelves,</hi> than to imitate <hi>what</hi> the <hi>fourth Age</hi> of the <hi>Church began</hi> to pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe, when the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt</hi> was near <hi>four hundred years old:</hi> The <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> themſelves are the <hi>Rule</hi> of <hi>her Faith,</hi> and for any <hi>Apoſtolical Practices ſhe</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires among <hi>them,</hi> who lived with the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> or <hi>neareſt to them;</hi> among whom finding <hi>nothing</hi> of any <hi>ſearching</hi> for <hi>Reliques,</hi> or <hi>any Miracles</hi> done by <hi>them</hi> in thoſe <hi>firſt three hundrid years,</hi> ſhe is reſolved to <hi>practiſe</hi> what the Chriſtians of <hi>thoſe firſt</hi> and <hi>pureſt Ages</hi> did, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than <hi>what After-ages</hi> did, wherein <hi>plenty</hi> and <hi>proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity</hi>
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:49186:18"/>let looſe the reins to <hi>ſome peoples fancies,</hi> and made <hi>that</hi> a part of <hi>Religion,</hi> which was never any before.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="charge_and_reply">
               <p>The <hi>fourteenth Article</hi> of <hi>Popery</hi> againſt me is <hi>that we freely</hi> grant, <hi>That the Fathers practiſed praying for the Dead; and owned it as advantageous to the Souls departed:</hi> And that I ſhould ſay that <hi>no body denys, That the Fathers in the firſt Ages us'd Oblations and Prayers for the Dead, and that theſe Prayers were offer'd up alſo for pardon of ſins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am extremely at a loſs to find how I am drawn in for <hi>Popery</hi> here, and which way <hi>it is</hi> proved upon me: All that I have done here is to <hi>own</hi> that the <hi>Fathers</hi> did practiſe thoſe things which I could not <hi>deny</hi> without betraying a greater <hi>Ignorance</hi> than I muſt pretend to in <hi>thoſe Writers,</hi> or that I have no conſcience at all. But muſt my Ingenuity then be made my crime? and muſt I be made a <hi>Papiſt</hi> for granting that, which I could not in my <hi>Circumſtances</hi> deny without making my ſelf a bold Lyar?</p>
               <p>I am fallen it ſeems into very bad hands, into the hands of One, who is reſoved to blacken me without having any regard to <hi>Truth</hi> or <hi>Juſtice,</hi> or <hi>Conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do not ſay one word there of my approving what <hi>thoſe Fathers</hi> did; I do not in the leaſt hint that I am for <hi>ſuch Practiſes,</hi> or that I ever uſe <hi>ſuch Prayers</hi> or <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations for the Dead,</hi> or ever intended to do it: So that this terrible Charge depends onely, and muſt reſt upon my granting <hi>ſuch Practices</hi> in former days.</p>
               <p>But is this dealing either juſt or reaſonable? at this rate he may make me a defender of any the moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary things, when I grant (as every man of conſcience muſt) that the <hi>generality</hi> of <hi>Fathers</hi> in the <hi>firſt Centuries</hi> believed a <hi>Millennium,</hi> am I to be made a <hi>Millenary</hi> for this? when I grant that for many Ages the <hi>Communion</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:49186:18"/>was given unto <hi>Infants,</hi> muſt I be concluded to be <hi>one</hi> that is of opinion that <hi>it</hi> ought to be ſo ſtill? or muſt I be repreſented thereupon to the world as <hi>one</hi> that does ſtill practiſe the thing, and gives the <hi>Communion</hi> unto the <hi>little Children.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How ridiculous ſoever ſuch falſe and extravagant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions appear to the world, yet the <hi>Uſage</hi> that I find from the <hi>Repreſenter's</hi> hands is exactly the ſame, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together as groundleſs as the <hi>other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Practices</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> her ſelf, which I do heartily ſubſcribe to; ſo far is ſhe from either <hi>encouraging</hi> or <hi>practiſing Prayers for the</hi> Dead, that whereas in the dawning of the <hi>Reformation</hi> in <hi>King Edwards</hi> firſt <hi>Common-Prayer Book</hi> there was a <hi>direct Praying for the Dead</hi> in that <hi>Prayer</hi> for the <hi>whole Eſtate of Chriſts Church;</hi> in the <hi>next Review</hi> of the <hi>Liturgy</hi> the <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions</hi> for the <hi>Dead</hi> were quite left out of <hi>that Prayer,</hi> and out of the <hi>whole Service.</hi> In the <hi>Common-Prayer Book</hi> printed at <hi>London</hi> in March 1549, the <hi>Prayer for the Dead</hi> is to be met with, and ſo it is in <hi>another Edition</hi> in <hi>June following</hi> in the <hi>ſame year</hi> at <hi>London:</hi> And in a <hi>Third Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of 1551. at <hi>Dublin;</hi> but upon the <hi>Review</hi> which was made about <hi>that time</hi> we find it omitted and quite left out of the <hi>Common-Prayer Books,</hi> printed in 1552, and <hi>after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> down to our times not <hi>any uſage</hi> or <hi>revival</hi> of that <hi>Practice</hi> among us.</p>
               <p>As to the <hi>Reaſons</hi> for leaving off that <hi>Practice</hi> which could pretend <hi>to ſo much Antiquity,</hi> I am not at leaſure, nor have Room here to ſet them down; I muſt confeſs that I am not at all ſatisfied of it from the <hi>beſt Inſtances</hi> for it.</p>
               <p>I cannot but look upon S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>'s <hi>praying</hi> for the <hi>Soul</hi> of the <hi>Emperor Theodoſius,</hi> and his reſolution <hi>not to leave
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:49186:19"/>him, till by his Tears and Prayers he had brought him unto the Mountain of the Lord, where he might enjoy Life for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vermore,</hi> as a <hi>Thing</hi> that might very well have been ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, nay that ought to have been ſpared, ſince we know by the <hi>very ſame Oration</hi> that Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> did believe that the <hi>Soul</hi> of <hi>that Emperour</hi> was in <hi>Bliſs, was placed in Heaven, did enjoy at that time perpetual Light,</hi> and a <hi>never ceaſing Tranquillity,</hi> and was admitted into the <hi>Society of the Saints in Glory.</hi> I have no other defence to make for this <hi>extraordinary Action</hi> of this <hi>Father,</hi> than to ſay that all this was done in a <hi>Rhetorical Harangue,</hi> wherein the <hi>Cuſtom</hi> of all times hath allowed the <hi>Orators</hi> to ſpeak things that were not <hi>ſtrict truths,</hi> and things which <hi>they</hi> neither properly ſpeaking <hi>believed</hi> themſelves, or were deſirous that <hi>others</hi> ſhould.</p>
               <p>And ſo in that <hi>celebrated Inſtance</hi> of Saint <hi>Auſtins</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for his <hi>Mother Monica</hi> after her deceaſe, <hi>that God would not enter into Judgment with her,</hi> and yet profeſſing in the very next words that <hi>he did believe that God had already done for her all that he did pray for;</hi> I am no more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to defend it, than I could the <hi>Prayers</hi> of any man whom <hi>God</hi> had bleſſed with <hi>Children</hi> and <hi>Heirs</hi> to his name and his Eſtate, if he ſhould be importunate with <hi>God</hi> that <hi>he</hi> would beſtow the bleſſing of <hi>Children</hi> upon him, and beſtow in his mercy but <hi>one Son</hi> upon <hi>him</hi> to keep up <hi>his family</hi> and <hi>his name.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do not mention theſe things to expoſe thoſe <hi>two ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Fathers,</hi> but to vindicate the <hi>Practice</hi> of <hi>my Mother-Church</hi> in relation to <hi>theſe things.</hi> I think <hi>thoſe</hi> that dye <hi>in the Lord</hi> have <hi>no need</hi> of our Prayers, and that <hi>thoſe</hi> that dye in <hi>his disfavonr</hi> can receive no <hi>benefit</hi> by <hi>them.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="charge_and_reply">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:49186:19"/>
               <p>The <hi>fifteenth Article</hi> againſt me is, that I ſay <hi>that it is the Opinion of his Church, that Chriſts Body is really preſent in the Euchariſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This charge is as ridiculous as any of the reſt, for if the <hi>real preſence</hi> be the <hi>Opinion</hi> of <hi>our Church,</hi> how comes it to be <hi>one</hi> of my <hi>Articles</hi> of <hi>Popery?</hi> Could this <hi>unreaſonable Adverſary</hi> have ſhewn that the <hi>Real Preſence</hi> is not the <hi>Opinion</hi> of <hi>our Church,</hi> but onely of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that I was a believer of <hi>ſuch</hi> a <hi>real Preſence,</hi> his charge againſt me of a <hi>Popiſh Opinion</hi> herein would have been moſt juſtly laid: But he neither offers to prove that <hi>our Church</hi> is not of <hi>that Opinion,</hi> nor is he at all able to do it, and yet I muſt be a <hi>Papiſt</hi> notwithſtanding I believe with <hi>our Church,</hi> whoſe <hi>real Preſence</hi> is far from looking like <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery,</hi> ſince <hi>ſhe</hi> hath ſo often and ſo fully declared that by <hi>real</hi> here is only meant a <hi>ſpiritual,</hi> not <hi>corporeal,</hi> or <hi>natural Preſence</hi> of <hi>Chriſts Body.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nay in that very place where I ſaid it was the <hi>Opinion</hi> of <hi>our Church</hi> that <hi>Chriſts Body was really preſent in the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt,</hi> I gave alſo the reaſon of that Opinion,
<q rend="margQuotes">becauſe we believe (as <hi>my words</hi>
                     <note n="(c)" place="margin">
                        <hi>p.</hi> 65.</note> there are) that the <hi>conſecrated Elements</hi> do by the Appointment of God <hi>communicate</hi> to every <hi>faithful Receiver</hi> the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Chriſt:</hi>
                  </q> which is no more than what S. <hi>Paul</hi> hath ſaid in other words before us, when he tells the <hi>Corinthians</hi> that the <hi>Bread</hi> which <hi>he</hi> and <hi>they</hi> broke was a <hi>Communion</hi> of, or did communicate to them, the <hi>Body of Chriſt,</hi> and that the <hi>Cup</hi> of <hi>Bleſſing</hi> was a <hi>Communion</hi> of the <hi>Blood of Chriſt.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.16.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="charge_and_reply">
               <p>The <hi>laſt Article of Popery</hi> againſt me is of the ſame nature with the <hi>former,</hi> that I do confeſs <hi>That that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:49186:20"/>Food is the Fleſh and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I do own that I did grant <hi>thoſe words</hi> as taken out of <hi>Juſtin Martyr,</hi> but had my <hi>Sly Adverſary</hi> but had the Honeſty to have put down the <hi>words</hi> that do imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately follow there, I am ſure that <hi>this</hi> would either not have been put down as an <hi>Article</hi> of my <hi>Popery,</hi> or that my <hi>Accuſer</hi> would have been hiſt at by all men for his folly in charging me with it, ſince immediately after thoſe words I did expreſs my ſelf thus;
<q rend="margQuotes">We have already granted that <hi>it is</hi> (to wit, that the <hi>Conſecrated Food is the Fleſh and Blood of Jeſus Chriſt)</hi> however to corrobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate what we ſaid above, it is evident to a Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that <hi>this conſecrated Food</hi> was ſtill <hi>Bread,</hi> and not <hi>tranſubſtantiated</hi> into the <hi>natural Body</hi> and <hi>Blood of Chriſt,</hi> becauſe S. <hi>Juſtin</hi> ſays at the <hi>ſame time</hi> and in the <hi>ſame ſentence</hi> that <hi>our Bodys are <hi>Nouriſhed</hi> by that very conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated Food;</hi> to affirm which of the <hi>Natural Fleſh</hi> of Chriſt is impious and deteſtable.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <p>Thus I have gone through, and fully anſwered this <hi>large Charge of Popery</hi> againſt me, and ſince he was not ſatisfied in the <hi>Letter</hi> to ſet them onely <hi>once</hi> down, but does for the greater ſecurity of effecting his deſigns a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt me, repeat them in ſhort before he ends his <hi>Letter,</hi> I will do the ſame here by <hi>my Anſwers</hi> unto <hi>them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt charge therefore in three <hi>Articles</hi> about the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the fourth about <hi>Tradition,</hi> I have ſhewn to be as Notorious and Scandalous a <hi>Falſification</hi> of a <hi>mans words</hi> and <hi>meaning</hi> as the <hi>greateſt Cheat</hi> in the world could be guilty of: that the <hi>ſix next</hi> can be called <hi>Popery</hi> onely by the <hi>ſame Figure</hi> that we would call the <hi>Belief of Chriſts Reſurrection Popery,</hi> becauſe <hi>all Chriſtians</hi> in the world believe <hi>it</hi> as well as the <hi>Church of Rome:</hi> which is a thing ſo horridly fooliſh, as no one but he that hath
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:49186:20"/>more <hi>Malice</hi> than <hi>Wit</hi> or <hi>Logick</hi> in his head could be ſuppoſed guilty of: and for the <hi>laſt ſix,</hi> they are moſt falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly nicknamed <hi>Popery,</hi> and moſt ridiculouſly laid to my <hi>particular charge;</hi> except this <hi>Malicious Adverſary</hi> can ſhew that to make a thing <hi>Popery</hi> it is neceſſary that it be believed and practiſed by <hi>all Churches</hi> that are againſt as well as for the <hi>Church of Rome;</hi> and that I am the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerality of Chriſtians,</hi> or at leaſt the <hi>whole Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If ever <hi>Rage</hi> and <hi>Folly, Malice</hi> and <hi>Weakneſs</hi> were equally diſcovered to the world, it certainly was in this <hi>wretched Letter,</hi> wherein all the care ſeems to be either to pervert my words, and falſifie my meaning, or to put down that as <hi>ſaid</hi> by me, which <hi>was not</hi> ſo; as <hi>meant</hi> by me, that <hi>was not</hi> ſo; and as <hi>ſaid</hi> by me <hi>in particular,</hi> which <hi>was common</hi> unto <hi>all Chriſtians.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding this <hi>injurious uſage</hi> of me, yet I cannot but thank the <hi>Repreſenter</hi> for it, ſince <hi>he</hi> hath by <hi>this Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> diſcovered to the world what ſort of <hi>perſon</hi> he is; and thereby given warning to the world to have a care how they believe <hi>One</hi> that will be guilty of ſuch diſhoneſt things; He may write on as long as he pleaſes, but this uſage of me will, I queſtion not, prevent his doing any miſchief by it, ſince <hi>Men</hi> are for reading <hi>thoſe Books</hi> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wherein they have reaſon to expect <hi>Truth, Candor</hi> and <hi>Integrity;</hi> and are always upon their guard againſt, if they vouchſafe to read, <hi>an Author</hi> that can and does write without <hi>any concern</hi> for <hi>Truth, Conſcience or Honeſty.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will before I conclude make <hi>one ſhort addreſs</hi> unto the <hi>Diſſenters,</hi> that they would have a care how they ſuffer themſelves to be impoſed upon in <hi>theſe things.</hi> I know <hi>this Author</hi> makes it his great care to keep them ſtill aloof off the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and therefore is <hi>upon every
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:49186:21"/>occaſion,</hi> nay <hi>without any occaſion</hi> ſtill putting them in mind of the <hi>late Execution</hi> of <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> and how they were haraſſed by <hi>them.</hi> But can they believe after all this that this man is their real <hi>Friend,</hi> whoſe <hi>Principles</hi> and <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices</hi> look quite another way? I think his affixing this <hi>moſt falſe</hi> and <hi>injurious Letter</hi> unto <hi>ſome</hi> of <hi>them</hi> is a fair warning how much real kindneſs <hi>he</hi> hath for them, who was ſo very deſirous to have <hi>this Letter</hi> thought by <hi>all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> to be <hi>theirs,</hi> which is made up of nothing elſe but <hi>folly, falſhood</hi> and <hi>ſlander.</hi> What is this but to have the world to believe that the <hi>Diſſenters</hi> are ſtill the <hi>ſame foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, falſe</hi> and <hi>ſlanderous people</hi> that <hi>moſt</hi> of <hi>his Church</hi> did uſe to think <hi>them,</hi> and I am affraid, do <hi>ſtill</hi> continue to do. I will trouble them no further, but requeſt <hi>this</hi> at <hi>their hands,</hi> that <hi>they</hi> would make it <hi>their Prayer</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> that they <hi>never may</hi> be guilty of the <hi>diſhonouring of God</hi> by af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fording their helping hand to the <hi>ruine</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:49186:21"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
